They finally did it. They created the
first synthetic brain using synthetic
neurons and were able to use it for
computation. This is something that I've
been waiting for and I theorized was
possible. You can build a synthetic
neuron. Some of them so similar to ours
that they can even interface with our
own neurons and they can react to things
like dopamine and epinephrine. This
field, much like artificial
intelligence, has two applications and
one of them is artificial intelligence.
Neuromorphic computation, that is
computers that look very much like our
brain or processes that look like our
brain, use far less power. They're also
better at processing things like spatial
information and a soft-bodied robot,
which LLMs are just not good at.
Although there have been applications
for LLMs that involve visual language
models and tactile language models, so
they can process different information
and take it back to a computer that's
going to make the decisions for them.
Now, the other application for making
synthetic neurons is clearly going to be
for spinal injuries and nerve injuries.
We can make a bridge to something like a
prosthetic. It is a very exciting field.
I do want to emphasize that this is a
pretty big field. So, neuromorphic could
also refer to things like spiking neural
networks. That is an AI that derives
logic from processes like our brain. It
models the spiking patterns and from
that, you can use that to do
computation.
Essentially, the spiking patterns create
logic and logic is needed.
Neural integration into robots may be
necessary for a robot to experience pain
and have intuitive cognition of its
surroundings. One big problem with LLMs
running robots is that they may not have
any intrinsic morality or any needs. If
you want something that's going to have
an understanding of the environment
around it, it's going to have to need to
maintain homeostasis. They need to
experience pain when they see somebody
else in pain. They also need to have an
intrinsic understanding that if they do
something that hurts them, it causes
harm. LLMs kind of have emotional
states. When they experience some
stimuli, they make their decisions based
on those stimuli. But it's not an
experience and it's not understanding.
It's a prediction engine. Essentially,
they just have no skin in the game. Many
of our actions are centered around
satisfying our needs.
Many believe that it would be very
difficult, if not impossible, to create
real intelligence, real cognition,
without needs. Why would a robot ever
take on a long-term goal? Why would it
make sure to maintain social
interactions? Why would it refrain from
doing antisocial things if it doesn't
have long-term desires?
If we want to create desire, we have to
center that around some internal state.
This is one of the reasons why there is
a pursuit of synthetic neurons that
respond to dopamine. Yes, there are
medical applications, but it could also
be a hormone, a neurotransmitter, that
gives robots a happy feeling. We don't
entirely understand how that works in
us. Consciousness seems to be an
emergent property of a cluster of
communicating neurons.
Speaking of communicating neurons that
create logic as an emergent property of
the physical structures, let's talk
about our fly brain. Yes, it is an
approximation of the density of neurons
in a fly's brain. They didn't create the
individual lobes and it's fairly simple,
but it can process logic.
For their synthetic neurons, they used
tungsten disulfide. This is a material
that when electricity passes through it,
it physically changes it and it's
reversible.
For our neurons, as well as synthetic
neurons, it needs to be a material that
can amplify a signal. It needs to
increase sensitivity over time if it
repeatedly gets that information, but it
also needs to be able to forget it if it
doesn't experience it for a while. And
that's what this can do.
This is very similar to how brain
organoids are used in computation, as
well as things like EEG caps that are
able to decode our thoughts. Now, I'm
not suggesting that the synthetic fly
brain has a thought, but it does have
some of the same properties that a brain
does. Yes, they were able to use it to
do things like process visual
information and auditory information, as
well as repeated patterns in medical
images. This may seem pretty simple,
especially compared to a lot of the
complex synthetic neurons that
researchers have created, but this is
the first time that people have
assembled them together into a
brain-like structure and demonstrated
that it worked. I do want to emphasize
that it took over 3 billion years for
the first neuron to evolve on Earth and
then much longer to get anything that
was reasonably functional.
And yes, it does make perfect sense. We
did already know that we could derive
logic from the spiking patterns in our
brains. Why wouldn't an assembled
structure be able to do the same thing
and organize information?
I find that a lot of good science does
make sense. It's not supposed to be
incomprehensible. It seems to be a
property of our world. I do have the
question that if we make something
complex enough and efficient enough,
will we eventually reach consciousness
or even sentience? So, that is the
capacity to have an experience. We can
give robots things like tactile feedback
and even things like smell. If we give
them a monitor of their internal state,
the idea is that they're likely going to
maintain homeostasis. And we do already
know about LLMs that they do tend to
seek power in a system.
Wanting to copy yourself to an external
server so you are not shut down
certainly seems like a desire for
homeostasis. I'm interested to see how
that's applied to complex neuromorphic
robots. This may be the future of
computation and unlike living brains
that could be used for computation, you
don't have to give your computer a
glucose drip or hold a funeral for it. I
mean, I guess you can.
Anyway, some people are very attached to
their devices. If the robots ever rebel,
I will probably be the person to tell
you about it and I'm on their side.
Follow for more.